<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="dhcp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>DHCP services</title>

  <section>
    <title>DHCP</title>

    <para>DHCP<indexterm>
        <primary>DHCP</primary>
      </indexterm> stands for Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol and is the
    de-facto standard for dynamic IP allocation. The basic premise is that a
    client, who does not know what IP address it has (or should have), asks it
    to the DHCP server. The flow used is shown in the next figure.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Standard DHCP flow</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/05-dhcp-flow.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Initially, the client does not know where the server is, so it
    broadcasts the DHCP discover request on the entire subnet. Network
    administrators will configure the routers on each subnet to forward the
    DHCP related messages to the proper server (actually enable a DHCP relay
    function in the router - forwarding alone is not sufficient), or can
    deploy DHCP Relay services in the subnet separate from the router.</para>

    <para>DHCP has a few advanced usages as well though.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Bootstrap Protocol</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>Bootstrap Protocol (BOOTP)</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>BOOTP</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>Bootstrap Protocol</primary>
        </indexterm> allows for a client to obtain not only IP address
      information, but also images that the client should download and boot.
      Unlike DHCP itself, which is usually triggered when the operating system
      on the client has already booted, BOOTP is meant to be executed before
      an operating system is loaded. Historically, BOOTP was created for
      diskless systems, but this feature is still used often.</para>

      <para>One of the situations where BOOTP can come in handy is to create
      bare metal backups of desktops. By default, the DHCP/BOOTP server does
      not pass any information back, and all desktops or workstations get no
      reply to the BOOTP requests and thus boot further into their operating
      system. But when a bare metal backup (or restore) needs to be executed,
      the administrator toggles the BOOTP server. When the workstation
      reboots, it now receives the necessary information from the BOOTP
      server, downloads an autonomous operating system image (such as a Linux
      OS with imaging software on it, such as PartImage) and performs the
      backup (or restore) operation that the administrator has
      configured.</para>

      <para>After backing up the file, the workstation is rebooted and the
      BOOTP server becomes silent again, allowing the workstation to continue
      to boot regularly.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Various DHCP options</title>

      <para>DHCP servers can pass on additional options to the clients, which
      are used to configure other services on the client. These options have
      unique integer as identifiers.</para>

      <para>Most of these options are to point the client to other centralized
      services, such as the syslog server to use (28), NTP Server (47-49),
      mail server (69) and more. If both server and clients are fully
      controlled by the organization, additional custom options can be used to
      configure systems further.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Architecture</title>

    <para>The basic setup shown further uses a high-available architecture
    where the DHCP services keep track of the leases granted to the systems,
    as well as balance free IP addresses between the two DHCP servers. This
    allows, if a network split occurs, that each DHCP service can act
    independently as it has its own pool of free IP addresses, and has
    knowledge of the lease state of all currently assigned addresses.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Standard HA architecture for DHCP</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/05-dhcp-ha.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <important>
      <para>Make sure that the two DHCP servers have their time synchronized,
      so the use of an NTP service for both systems is seriously
      recommended.</para>
    </important>

    <section>
      <title>Flows and feeds</title>

      <para>No flows or feeds are identified as of yet.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Administration</title>

      <para>To administer DHCPd, a configuration management tool (puppet) is
      used to update configurations. Regular operations on the DHCP daemon
      (stopping/starting) is done through the standard Unix services.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Administering DHCPd</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/05-dhcp-admin.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Monitoring</title>

      <para>To monitor DHCP operations, log events need to be captured. This
      allows the monitoring infrastructure to follow up on the IP pool
      balance.</para>

      <para>On regular times, the following log entries will be shown with the
      current balancing information:</para>

      <programlisting>Oct 24 09:33:21 src &lt;at&gt; intranet dhcpd: pool 8124898 total 759 free 238 backup 266 lts -14
Oct 24 09:33:32 src &lt;at&gt; intranet dhcpd: pool 8124898 total 759 free 237 backup 266 lts -14</programlisting>

      <para>In the above example, from a pool with currently 759 IP addresses,
      237 are not assigned and "owned" by the server while the backup server
      has 266 IP addresses free. The lts parameter (which stands for "leases
      to send") tells that the system is to receive 14 leases (negative
      number) in order to balance the available IP addresses.</para>

      <para>Other monitoring is of course </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Operations</title>

      <para>In standard operation mode, the DHCP daemon receives requests and
      updates from DHCP relay services (or directly from servers in the same
      subnet). Any activity is logged through the system logger, who forwards
      the events to the log server for further processing.</para>

      <para>An NTP service is explicitly mentioned on the drawing as time
      synchronisation is very important for the fail-over setup of the DHCP
      service.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Operational flows and activities on DHCP service</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/05-dhcp-operations.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Users</title>

      <para>The DHCP daemon is an anonymous service; no users are defined
      beyond the administrators (on operating system level).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Security</title>

      <para>ISC DHCP is a popular components, so exploits are not that hard to
      find against older versions.</para>

      <para>Make sure that the DHCP service is running on the latest patch
      level, and is properly hardened.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>ISC DHCP</title>

    <para>When you have systems that require dynamically allocated IP
    addresses, you will need a DHCP service.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Installation and configuration</title>

      <para>The installation and configuration of DHCP is fairly simple and,
      similar to BIND, uses flat files for its configuration.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Installation</title>

        <para>First install the DHCP server.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>emerge dhcp</command></programlisting>

        <para>Do the same on the relay servers.</para>

        <para>Next, edit <filename>/etc/conf.d/dhcpd</filename> to configure
        the DHCP daemon to use IPv6.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>cat /etc/conf.d/dhcpd</command>
DHCPD_OPTS="-6"</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Master DHCP server</title>

        <para>On the master DHCP server, configure the
        <filename>/etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf</filename> file similar to the
        following:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>cat /etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf</command>
ddns-update-style interim;

authorative;

default-lease-time 600;
max-lease-time 7200;

server-identifier adhcpp.internal.genfic.com;
failover peer "dhcp-ha" {
  primary;
  split 128;
  mclt 3600;
  address 2001:db8:81:e2::fe12; # This server
  port 519;
  peer address 2001:db8:81:e4::822f; # Secondary server
  peer port 519;
  max-response-delay 60;
  max-unacked-updates 10;
  load balance max seconds 3;
};

# Shared part

subnet6 2001:db8:81:e2::/64 {
  range6 2001:db8:81:e2::f00 2001:db8:81:e2::fff;
  option dhcp6.name-servers 2001:db8:81:21::ac:98ad:5fe1, \
    2001:db8:81:22::ae:6b01:e3d8;
  option dhcp6.domain-search "workstation.internal.genfic.com";
}

subnet6 2001:db8:81:21::/64 {
  # Empty but must be declared so DHCPd starts
}</programlisting>

        <para>It is also possible to have the DHCP server provide a fixed IP
        address to a system based on its MAC address. This is handled through
        the host parameter:</para>

        <programlisting>group {
  use-host-decl-names on;

  host la00010 {
    hardware ethernet "e8:0c:11:31:9f:0b";
    fixed-address la00010.workstation.internal.genfic.com;
    option host-name "la00010";
  }
}</programlisting>

        <para>Finally, start the service and register it to automatically
        start during boot.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>rc-update add dhcpd default</command>
# <command>rc-service dhcpd start</command></programlisting>

        <para>On the secondary server, the failover part of the configuration
        would look like so:</para>

        <programlisting>server-identifier adhcps.internal.genfic.com;
failover peer "dhcp-ha" {
  secondary;
  address 2001:db8:81:e4::822f; # This server
  port 519;
  peer address 2001:db8:81:e2::fe12; # Primary server
  peer port 519;
  max-response-delay 60;
  max-unacked-updates 10;
  load balance max seconds 3;
};</programlisting>

        <para>The remainder of the configuration file is the same as on the
        master.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Relay services</title>

        <para>To configure a relay service, edit
        <filename>/etc/conf.d/dhcrelay</filename> and set the DHCRELAY_OPTS
        accordingly.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>cat /etc/conf.d/dhcrelay</command>
DHCRELAY_OPTS="-6 -l eth0 -u 2001:db8:81:21::f4:3303:40f4%eth0 -u \
  2001:db8:81:22::5f:3853:fe78%eth0"</programlisting>

        <para>Also edit <filename>/etc/init.d/dhcrelay</filename> as it forces
        two options that are only valid for IPv4:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>vim /etc/init.d/dhcrelay</command>
(... 1. look for $(printf " -i %s" ${IFACE}) and delete it ...)
(... 2. look for DHCRELAY_SERVERS and remove it ...)
(... End result should be something like:)
start-stop-daemon --start --exec /usr/sbin/dhcrelay \
  -- -q ${DHCRELAY_OPTS}</programlisting>

        <para>Then start up the relay service and make sure it starts at boot
        time as well.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>rc-update add dhcrelay default</command>
# <command>rc-service dhcrelay start</command></programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Logging</title>

      <para>For the DHCP service, log entries are sent to the system
      logger.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resources</title>

    <para>On ISC DHCP:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link
        xlink:href="http://www.madboa.com/geek/dhcp-failover/">High-available
        DHCP with failover</link> (IPv4 only) (Madboa.com)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
