<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="buildserver"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>A Gentoo build server</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>To support multiple Gentoo Linux hosts, we will be creating a build
    server. But just having one server build packages isn't sufficient - we
    need to be able to</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>have separate build environments based on a number of different
        "templates" that will be used in our architecture.</para>

        <para>Because of Gentoo's flexibility, we will have systems that have
        different USE flags, CFLAGS or other settings. All these settings
        however need to be constant for the build service to work well. If
        deviations are small, it is possible to use the majority of the build
        server and still use local compilations, but in our architecture, we
        will assume that the build server offers the binaries for all systems
        and that systems by themselves usually do not need to build code
        themselves.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>support phased builds across the architecture</para>

        <para>Our architecture supports both production and non-production
        systems. The non-production systems are used to stage updates and
        validate changes before pushing them to production (this for quality
        assurance as well as a better service availability). This does mean
        that we need to be able to "fix" the repositories once we deem them
        stable enough, and then work on a new one.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>provide access to stable tree</para>

        <para>Any client that wishes to use the build server will need access
        to that build servers' portage tree and overlays (if applicable). As
        the tree is only needed in case of updates, there is little point in
        having this tree available on the clients at all times.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>limit host access to authorized systems</para>

        <para>We want to limit access to the built packages to authorized
        systems only. This both to prevent "production" systems to
        accidentally take in non-production data, as well as ensure that only
        systems we manage ourselves are accessing the system. By using
        host-based authorizations, we can also follow up on systems more
        easily (such as logging).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>and this is just a subset of the requirements that are involved in
    the build server.</para>

    <para>When you make a simple build server design, you immediately see that
    a multitude of other components are needed. These include</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>a DNS server to offer round-robin access to the build
        servers</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>a certificate server to support management of certificates in
        the organization</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>a high-available NFS server to host the built packages on</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>a scheduler to execute builds</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Some of these have been discussed already, others can be integrated
    nicely afterwards.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Building a build server</title>

    <para>Setting up a build server requires building the server. It comes to
    no surprise that we will not be benefiting from a build server initially
    here, but once the build infrastructure is set up, we might be able to use
    the existing build results (which will be stored on the NFS server) to
    recreate the build infrastructure.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Setup build host</title>

      <para>The build host is most likely a dedicated (i.e. non-virtualized)
      system because it will be very CPU and memory hungry and can use all the
      resources it can have. As a result though, it means that our build
      host(s) should be set up in a multi-active setup. Each buildhost then
      runs a web server (like lighttpd) which hosts the built package
      locations as the document root of the virtual hosts. To support the
      multiple build profiles, we will use different IP-based virtual hosts
      and control access to them through a certificate-based access list to
      only allow authorized hosts to download packages from the server. I opt
      to use web-based disclosure of packages instead of network mounts as
      they offer more control, easier logging, etc.</para>

      <para>The build server itself will use a simple configuration scheme and
      a few scripts that are either triggered manually or scheduled centrally.
      These scripts will pull in the necessary changes (be it updates in
      overlays or in the main portage tree) and do full system builds. The
      resulting packages will be stored in NFS-mounted locations (where the
      NFS server is set up high available).</para>

      <section>
        <title>Build profile configuration</title>

        <para>Let's first start with the build profile configuration. We will
        use <command>catalyst</command><indexterm>
            <primary>catalyst</primary>
          </indexterm>, Gentoo's release management tool that is used to
        generate the weekly releases. With some tweaks, it can be easily used
        to support our build server.</para>

        <para>Our build setup will do something akin to the following:</para>

        <programlisting>Daily:
+- Fetch new portage tree snapshot
+- For each build profile:
   +- Put snapshot in &lt;storedir&gt;/snapshots
   +- Build stage3 (using catalyst)
   `- Build grp (using catalyst)

Weekly (and before daily): 
`- For each build profile
   `- Update spec file to now point to most recent stage3</programlisting>

        <para>The setup will assume that a working stage3 tarball already
        exists and is made for further use. If that is not the case, you will
        need to get a fresh stage3 first and put it in
        <filename>&lt;storedir&gt;/builds</filename>. From that point onwards,
        this stage3 is reused for the new stage3. Binary packages are kept as
        those will be used for the binary host later. The grp build (which
        stands for Gentoo Reference Platform) will then build the remainder of
        binary packages.</para>

        <para>So let's first install catalyst.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>emerge catalyst</command></programlisting>

        <para>Next, we make an initial configuration for catalyst. One set of
        configuration files matches one build profile, so you'll need to
        repeat the next steps for each build profile you want to support.
        We'll start with the generic catalyst configuration, use
        <filename>/srv/build</filename> as the base directory for all related
        activities under which each build profile will have its top level. In
        the next example, where you see "basic_bp", it is the name of this
        build profile.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>mkdir -p /srv/build/basic_bp/{portage,portage_settings,snapshot_cache,catalyst_store}</command>
# <command>cd /etc/catalyst</command>
# <command>cat catalyst-basic_bp.conf</command>
digests="sha512"
contents="auto"
distdir="/usr/portage/distfiles"
envscript="/etc/catalyst/catalystrc"
hash_function="crc32"
options="autoresume metadata_overlay pkgcache seedcache snapcache"
portdir="/srv/build/basic_bp/portage"
sharedir="/usr/lib64/catalyst"
snapshot_cache="/srv/build/basic_bp/snapshot_cache"
storedir="/srv/build/basic_bp/catalyst_store"</programlisting>

        <para>Next, create the <filename>stage3.spec</filename> and
        <filename>grp.spec</filename> files. The templates for these files can
        be found in
        <filename>/usr/share/doc/catalyst-&lt;version&gt;/examples</filename>.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>cat stage3-basic_bp.conf</command>
## Static settings
subarch: amd64
target: stage3
rel_type: default
profile: hardened/linux/amd64/no-multilib/selinux
cflags: -O2 -pipe -march=native
portage_confdir: /srv/build/basic_bp/portage_settings
## Dynamic settings (might be passed on as parameters instead)
# Name of the "seed" stage3 file to use
source_subpath: stage3-amd64-20120401
# Name of the portage snapshot to use
snapshot: 20120406
# Timestamp to use on your resulting stage3 file
version_stamp: 20120406

# <command>cat grp-basic_bp.conf</command>
(... similar as to stage3 ...)
grp/packages: lighttpd nginx cvechecker bind apache ...</programlisting>

        <para>The <parameter>portage_confdir</parameter> variable tells
        catalyst where to find the portage configuration specific files (all
        those you usually put in <filename>/etc/portage</filename>).</para>

        <para>The <parameter>source_subpath</parameter> variable tells
        catalyst which stage3 file to use as a seed file. You can opt to point
        this one to the stage3 built the day before or to a fixed value,
        whatever suits youµ the best. This file needs to be stored inside
        <filename>/srv/build/basic_bp/catalyst_store/builds</filename>.</para>

        <para>Copy the portage snapshot (here,
        <filename>portage-20120406.tar.bz</filename>2) and related files in
        <filename>/srv/build/basic_bp/catalyst_store/snapshots</filename>. If
        you rather create your own snapshot, populate
        <filename>/srv/build/basic_bp/portage</filename> with the tree you
        want to use, and then call catalyst to generate a snapshot for you
        from it:</para>

        <warning>
          <para>The grSecurity chroot restrictions that are enabled in the
          kernel will prohibit catalyst from functioning properly. It is
          advisable to disable the chroot restrictions when building through
          catalyst. You can toggle them through <command>sysctl</command>
          commands.</para>
        </warning>

        <programlisting># <command>catalyst -c catalyst-basic_bp.conf -s 20120406</command></programlisting>

        <para>Next, we have the two catalyst runs executed to generate the new
        stage3 (which will be used by subsequent installations as the new
        "seed" stage3) and grp build (which is used to generate the binary
        packages).</para>

        <programlisting># <command>catalyst -c catalyst-basic_bp.conf -f stage3-basic_bp.conf</command>
# <command>catalyst -c catalyst-basic_bp.conf -f grp-basic_bp.conf</command></programlisting>

        <para>When the builds have finished, you will find the packages for
        this profile in
        <filename>/srv/build/basic_bp/catalyst_store/builds</filename>. These
        packages can then be moved to the NFS mount later.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Automating the builds</title>

        <para>To automate the build process, remove the date-specific
        parameters and instead pass them on as parameters, like so:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>catalyst -c catalyst-basic_bp.conf -f stage3-basic_bp.conf -C version_stamp=20120406</command></programlisting>

        <para>Next, if the grp build finishes succesfully as well, we can use
        rsync to:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>synchronize the binary packages from
            <filename>/srv/build/basic_bp/catalyst_store/packages/default/stage3-amd64-&lt;version_stamp&gt;</filename>
            to the NFS mount for this particular profile, as well as rsync the
            portage tree used (as these two need to be synchronized).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>copy the portage tree snapshot to the NFS mount for this
            particular profile, while signing it to support GPG-validated
            web-rsyncs.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>rsync the content of the
            <parameter>portage_confdir</parameter> location to the NFS
            mount</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>The combination of these three allow us to easily update
        clients:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Update <filename>/etc/portage</filename> (locally) using the
            stored <parameter>portage_confdir</parameter> settings</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Update the local portage tree using emerge-webrsync (with
            GPG validation)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Update the system, using the binaries created by the build
            server</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Update the eix catalogue</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>The following two scripts support this in one go (fairly small
        scripts - modify to your liking) although we will be using a different
        method for updating the systems later.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>cat autobuild</command>
#!/bin/sh

# Build Profile
BP="basic_bp"
# Time Stamp
TS="$(date +%Y%m%d)"
# Build Directory
BD="/srv/build/${BP}"
# Packages Directory
PD="${BD}/catalyst_store/packages/default/stage3-${TS}"

catalyst -c /etc/catalyst/catalyst-${BP}.conf \
         -f /etc/catalyst/stage3-${BP}.conf \
         -C version_stamp=${TS} || exit 1
catalyst -c /etc/catalyst/catalyst-${BP}.conf \
         -f /etc/catalyst/grp-${BP}.conf \
         -C version_stamp=${TS} || exit 2
rsync -avug ${PD}/ /nfs/${BP}/packages || exit 3
cp ${BD}/catalyst_store/builds/portage-${TS}.tar.bz2 /nfs/${BP}/snapshots || exit 4
gpg --armor --sign \
    --output /nfs/${BP}/snapshots/portage-${TS}.tar.bz2.gpg \
    /nfs/${BP}/snapshots/portage-${TS}.tar.bz2 || exit 5
tar cvjf ${BD}/portage_settings /nfs/${BP}/portage_settings-${TS}.tar.bz2 || exit 6</programlisting>

        <programlisting># <command>cat autoupdate</command>
#!/bin/sh

# Build Profile
BP="basic_bp"
# Edition
ED="testing"
# Time Stamp to use
TS="$1"

wget https://${BP}-${ED}.builds.genfic.com/${BP}/${ED}/portage_settings-${TS}.tar.bz2
tar xvjf -C /etc/portage portage_settings-${TS}.tar.bz2
restorecon -R /etc/portage
emerge-webrsync --revert=${TS}
emerge -uDNg world
eix-update</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Promoting editions</title>

        <para>The automated builds will do daily packaging for the "testing"
        edition. Once in a while though, you will want to make a snapshot of
        it and promote it to production. Most of these activities will be done
        on the NFS server though (we will be using LVM snapshots). The clients
        still connect to the build servers for their binaries (although this
        is not mandatory - you can host other web servers with the same mount
        points elsewhere to remove the stress of the build servers) but "poll"
        in the snapshot location (by using a different edition).</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Enabling the web server</title>

      <para>We will be using lighttpd as the web server of choice for the
      build server. The purpose of the web server is to disclose the end
      result of the builds towards the clients.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Installing and configuring lighttpd</title>

        <para>First install lighttpd:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>emerge lighttpd</command></programlisting>

        <para>Next, configure the web server with the sublocations you want to
        use. We will be using IP-based virtual hosts because we will be using
        SSL-based authentication and access control. Since SSL handshakes
        occur before the HTTP headers are sent, we cannot use name-based
        virtual hosts. The downside is that you will need additional IP
        addresses to support each build target:</para>

        <programlisting>build-basic.internal.genfic.com          (IP1)
build-basic.testing.internal.genfic.com  (IP2)
build-ldap.internal.genfic.com           (IP3)
build-ldap.testing.internal.genfic.com   (IP4)</programlisting>

        <para>These aliases are used for the packages (and tree) for the build
        profiles "basic" and "ldap" (you can generate as many as you want).
        Each build profile has two "editions", one is called testing (and
        contains the daily generated ones), the other production (which is the
        tested one). You might create a "snapshot" edition as well, to prepare
        for a new production build.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>cat lighttpd.conf</command>
var.log_root            = "/var/log/lighttpd"
var.server_root         = "/var/www/localhost"
var.state_dir           = "/var/run/lighttpd"

server.use-ipv6         = "enable"
server.username         = "lighttpd"
server.groupname        = "lighttpd"
server.document-root    = server_root + "/htdocs"
server.pid-file         = state_dir + "/lighttpd.pid"

server.errorlog         = log_root + "/error.log"

$SERVER["socket"] == "IP1:443" {
ssl.engine             = "enable"
ssl.pemfile            = "/etc/ssl/private/basic-production-server.pem"
ssl.ca-file            = "/etc/ssl/certs/production-crtchain.crt"
ssl.verifyclient.activate      = "enable"
ssl.verifyclient.enforce       = "enable"
ssl.verifyclient.depth         = 2
ssl.verifyclient.exportcert    = "enable"
ssl.verifyclient.username      = "SSL_CLIENT_S_DN_CN"
server.document-root    = "/nfs/build/production/basic"
server.error-log        = log_root + "/basic/error.log"
accesslog.filename      = log_root + "/basic/access.log"
}

$SERVER["socket"] == "1IP2:443" {
ssl.engine              = "enable"
ssl.pemfile             = "/etc/ssl/private/basic-testing-server.pem"
ssl.ca-file             = "/etc/ssl/certs/testing-crtchain.crt"
ssl.verifyclient.activate      = "enable"
ssl.verifyclient.enforce       = "enable"
ssl.verifyclient.depth         = 2
ssl.verifyclient.exportcert    = "enable"
ssl.verifyclient.username      = "SSL_CLIENT_S_DN_CN"
server.document-root    = "/nfs/build/testing/basic"
server.error-log        = log_root + "/basic.testing/error.log"
accesslog.filename      = log_root + "/basic.testing/access.log"
}</programlisting>

        <para>The configuration file can be extended with others (it currently
        only includes the definitions for the "basic" build profile). As you
        can see, different certificates are used for each virtual host.
        However, the <parameter>ssl.ca-file</parameter> points to a chain of
        certificates that is only applicable to either production or testing
        (and not both). This ensures that production systems (with a
        certificate issued by production CA) cannot succesfully authenticate
        against a testing address and vice versa.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Managing lighttpd</title>

        <para>The log files for the lighttpd server are stored in
        /var/log/lighttpd. It is wise to configure logrotate to rotate the log
        files. In the near future, we will reconfigure this towards a central
        logging configuration.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Security benchmark</title>

        <para>TODO:</para>

        <programlisting>server.username and server.groupname must not be root
server.tag = "webserver" to not disclose version information
index-ffle.names = ( "index.php", "index.html" ) -&gt; which files to use for directory listings
dir-listing.activate = "disabled" -&gt; disable generation of directory listings
enable mod_access + url.access-deny = ("~", ".inc") -&gt; disable access to backup files
enable ssl
ssl.use-sslv2 = "disable"
access log only writable for user, readable by group (is group membership ok for the rest?)
same for error log
</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resources</title>

    <para>Catalyst:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>TODO</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Lighttpd:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://calomel.org/lighttpd.html">Lighttpd
        tutorial</link> (Calomel.org)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
