<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
  <title>A Gentoo Linux Advanced Reference Architecture</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <title>A Gentoo Linux Advanced Reference Architecture</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Sven</firstname>

      <surname>Vermeulen</surname>
    </author>

    <authorblurb>
      <para>
      Sven Vermeulen is an ICT Architect who enjoys working on Gentoo Linux
      in his spare time. Within the Gentoo Linux project, he is a documentation
      developer, largely to blame for the Gentoo Handbook and a large number of
      Gentoo-related guides, and a Gentoo Hardened developer in charge for
      Gentoo's SELinux support. You can find him online under the alias "SwifT"
      or reach him through his e-mail address "sven.vermeulen@siphos.be".
      </para>
    </authorblurb>

    <abstract>
      <para>
        The book "A Gentoo Linux Advanced Reference Architecture" is meant as a
	resource displaying the powerful features of many free software
	solutions that are supported on top of Gentoo Linux. It is a deep-dive
	approach in many aspects related to processes, supportability,
	maintainability based on Gentoo Linux system deployments.
      </para>
      <para>
        Unlike the existing, per-application documents that exist on the
	Internet (and which are a valuable resource to get into the gory details
	of many applications) and the per-distribution guides that provide
	information on using that particular distribution, this book will focus
	more on architecturing IT infrastructure for medium-sized enterprises.
	Smaller enterprises might find the reference architecture here too
	expensive or large - however, many services described in the book can be
	slimmed down into a smaller deployment as well.
      </para>
      <para>
        It is seriously recommended to have a good grasp of what Gentoo Linux is
	to start with. The other online resource ("Linux Sea") can be a good
	introduction to Gentoo Linux, but that might not be sufficient to
	appreciate the detail and organization of this book.
      </para>
      <para>
        This book will progress rather slowly (compared to the initial development
	of "Linux Sea" as its content will be written down as I teach myself the
	technologies mentioned within. When the development of this book started,
	knowledge about the technical services described later is still limited, and 
	the book will be used as a sort-of progress report by the author. Call it
	offsite knowledge storage ;-)
      </para>
      <para>
        The version you are reading currently is v0.08 and has been generated
	on 2012/04/21.
      </para>
    </abstract>

    <edition>GLARA v0.08</edition> <!-- Update above paragraph too!! -->

    <copyright>
      <year>2012</year>

      <holder>Sven Vermeulen</holder>
    </copyright>
    
    <legalnotice>
      <para>
        You are free to share (copy, distribute and transmit) the work as well
        as remix (adapt) the work under the conditions of the Creative Commons
        Attribution Noncommercial Share Alike 2.0 license, available at
        http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/be/deed.en
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc></toc>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="aglara/01-architecturing.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="aglara/02-platform.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="aglara/03-networkservices.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="aglara/04-certificates.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="aglara/05-nfs.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="aglara/06-buildserver.xml" />
  <!-- <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="glossary.xml" /> -->
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="genindex.sgm" />

</book>
